[♪ western music plays]
[narrator, in English] A few months ago.
Monument Valley, Utah.
[Noel, in Japanese] Chaka, Umi, Shizu.
I came up with this itinerary
to share this majestic scenery with you.
[narrator] It's the special summer break
Noel organized
for the Travis Japan members.
At the foot of the Rocky Mountains
where the desert winds blow
lies the real America
the members have yet to see.
The Travis Japan members except for Noel
divide up into two groups
and head to their final destination.
Sedona, Arizona.
Noel sets out to Sedona on his own
before the others
to quietly prepare
a warm welcome for them.
[♪ opening theme music plays]
Travis Japan
SUMMER VACATION!! IN THE USA
[in Japanese] The vast and breathtaking
Monument Valley is on a Navajo tribe land.
It is located on the
southern Utah-northern Arizona border.
This classic American landscape is defined
by the towering sandstones
known as "buttes,"
which can reach
up to 300 meters in height.
This place is famous for its role
in various films.
All right.
This is the Utah landscape.
Hurry up.
[Umi] What's going on, Kaito?
What are you doing?
This is where Forrest Gump was filmed.
The breeze!
This is the very road Forrest runs on.
That's right.
Forrest Gump zipped right through here.
[in English] "My name is Forrest Gump."
Your name is Chaka.
You are not Forrest Gump.
Hi, my name is Forrest Gump.
-[Umi, in Japanese] No, no.
-[Shizu laughs]
-Care if I recreate the iconic scene?
-What scene?
What are you about to do?
Ready?
[Umi] Yeah. Go for it.
Kaito?
See ya!
-[Umi] Wanna chase him?
-[Shizu] Should we?
[♪ upbeat music plays]
I have America in the palm of my hands.
[laughs]
[♪ upbeat music continues]
[♪ music ends]
[Umi] There's way more visitors here
than the other campsite.
-[Shizu] You mean, compared to Moab?
-[Umi] Yeah.
-[Chaka] We're going to camp out tonight.
-Okay.
[Umi] Finally?
We're finally going to do it.
We're sleeping in a tent, not the RV.
-A tent?
-Here it comes!
[Shizu] Love the camp vibe.
[Chaka] This is really starting
to feel like camping.
[Umi] This is the most authentic
camp setup we've had so far.
[Chaka] Gimme a sec.
We have leftover sausage links
from the grocery run.
-Good idea. Let's toss it in.
-We're using it?
It'll turn out delicious.
Then this one… I'll do it once Umi's done.
Got it.
We might have a cutting board.
[Chaka] Nice.
[Umi] Okay!
Can we make vegetable stir fry
with sausage?
[Shizu] Is that the sausage?
[Umi] Gotta use up the leftovers.
I never know how many layers
I'm supposed to peel.
[Shizu] To the white layer is fine.
-[Umi] White is good? Not green?
-[Shizu] White or the green. That's right.
-How about this?
-You got it.
[Umi] Hold on, how can you see its color
through those shades?
-I can see it, I promise.
-[Umi] Hey!
-My eyes are sensitive from the sun…
-You've peeled it enough.
…so I have to keep them on.
[Umi] Let's see…
This means I'm in charge
of the cutlery, yeah?
[Chaka] Let's load it up. There.
[Shizu] Ta-da!
-[Chaka] Bon appétit.
-[Umi] Sautéed sausage, peppers and onion.
[Chaka] Yum-yum, it's da best.
Thanks for the impeccable teamwork, guys.
Hands together.
-Thanks for the meal.
Well then…
-[in English] Cheers!
-Cheers!
-[in Japanese] Well…
-I'm craving curry.
-Time to dig in.
-Time to eat.
Yum.
The potatoes are fluffy.
Heck yes!
The meat isn't tough either.
-Yup.
-Yeah.
Everything's cooked to perfection.
[Shizu] You know how you randomly
wake up at night sometimes?
-[Chaka] Sure.
-[Umi] Yeah.
If I wake up tonight,
then it'll be to your sleeping faces.
-Except when we're sleeping, we look…
-Like little angels.
-Was that memorable?
-It really is nice.
We work together,
but it's not like we're ever
together for bedtime.
[Umi] Right.
That only happens when
we're on a trip together like this.
-We're usually awake at work.
-You get my drift.
[laughs] Well, that too.
-It'd be crazy if we dozed off at work.
-Well, yeah.
Still, it's nice.
[Chaka] The vibe changes depending on
who's around.
When it's just me and Shizuya,
or just you two,
or the three of us together,
-the vibe is a bit different.
-[Umi] It's a little different, yeah.
So far, the good far outweighs the bad.
[Shizu] Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
This is day four,
but I still feel that way.
[Shizu] Yeah.
We're well aware of
each other's shortcomings.
[Umi] It's true.
[fire crackles]
[Shizu] Phew, hot!
-Umi, is yours done?
-Not yet.
-It's ready to come off the fire isn't it?
-No, you want it almost burned.
That's the whole point
of toasting marshmallow.
-Or else you're making warmed marshmallow.
-[laughs]
-A little burnt is good?
-It's bubbly! There you have it.
Nice and toasty.
[Umi] Say, I had a thought.
-[Chaka] Yeah?
-[Shizu] Okay.
I wonder why Noel
paired up the three of us.
Good question.
I wonder why.
Maybe…
He wanted to see the three of us united.
Yeah. Good guess.
We can only guess.
We've been surrounded by
a lot of nature on this trip.
-Right.
-Camping too.
-It almost feels like we're off the grid.
-True.
Then…
We've had to trek through the wilderness
with our own two feet.
-So maybe…
-Right.
Maybe he wanted us to learn
to rely on each other.
-Ah.
-And that's why he chose nature for us.
We might develop
new perspectives to things.
[Shizu] Right.
-And make new discoveries.
-Right, I agree.
-We don't know his exact reasoning yet.
-[Shizu] Yeah.
Which probably means…
that we haven't quite found it.
Right.
That's why I hope we'll find the answer
by the time our trip comes to an end.
[Shizu] Right.
We'll come to learn the truth then.
-[Chaka] Hopefully we can figure it out.
-[Umi] Right.
[Noel] Yes, that's it.
I carefully picked out these locations
because I wanted everyone
to set their sights
on the path ahead for Travis Japan.
There's no better place on earth
for meditation than here, after all.
You're due to discover
what I mean tomorrow.
I can't wait to see how you'll react.
-[in English] Good morning.
-Good morning.
Hi. Good afternoon.
-[in Japanese] Today, we're already here…
-Yup.
…at Monument Valley Tribal Park.
-Whoa…
-Here we are.
This is Monument Valley.
-How amazing.
-Seriously.
-We arrived at Monument Valley last night.
-Yeah.
Let's see what Noel's itinerary
has in store for us today.
[Noel] Monument Valley sits
within the Navajo Nation.
Which is the name of the largest
Native American reservation and tribe
in the United States.
The Navajo Tribe has resided
on this sacred land since 2,000 BC.
With a Navajo guide by your side,
you are allowed access
to a restricted area.
I want the three members to encounter
the raw Navajo Tribe culture.
Or should I say, the raw America.
[in English] I know you guys probably…
the first time here in Monument Valley?
-[in English] Yes, first time.
-Yes.
This is our motherland. Homeland. Welcome.
Thank you so much.
Um, since you guys are here
the first time,
um, the proper way of
who we are as people…
We call ourself Diné. Diné.
-Diné.
-Yes.
The Navajo name is more of a…
a secondary name and all that.
It was given to us.
Our original name is Diné.
-Diné.
-Yes.
Well, are you guys ready to have
some adventure today in Monument Valley?
-Sure.
-Yeah.
We can step in right here.
-Yay! Let's go!
-Yeah.
That's… Can we…
Yeah.
[Umi, Shizu, Chaka laugh]
[in Japanese] Whoa, this is unreal.
[Shizu, in English]
That's adventure. [laughs]
[Noel, in Japanese]
Our guide is Mr. Harold Simpson,
a Diné descendant and storyteller.
Mr. Simpson, who grew up on
this sacred land called Monument Valley,
recounts the memories of the Diné
through the language and the songs
passed down by his forefathers.
[Shizu whoops]
-[Umi] Destination. Did we reach it?
-[Shizu] What a nice day.
[Chaka, in English] Wow. Huge.
[Shizu] Whoa.
[Harold, in English] This is a place
called Mitten Buttes. Okay?
Before I get into it,
I'm pretty sure everything that you
see here is fabulous and all that.
Wonderful, beautiful and all that.
In… My introduction
to the Navajo way of life is…
[speaks Navajo]
[in English] My introduction
would be my mother's clan
is the Before Dawn People.
My father's clan
is the Bitter Water clan people.
My maternal grandfather's clan
is the Red House Towering People clan.
My paternal grandfather's clan
is the Yucca Fruit People clan.
And those four clan
plays a big part in my life.
And that's how we
introduce ourself with people.
[tour guide speaks indistinctly]
Hey!
-That's my brother.
-Yeah, really?
-Hi, nice to meet you.
-Richard.
Yeah, Richard.
-This rock that sits right over here?
-[Chaka] Mm-hmm.
It is called… [speaks Navajo]
-[Chaka speaks Navajo]
-[speaks Navajo]
-[Chaka, in English] Tree?
-[Harold speaks Navajo]
[Harold, in English] …means, um, "red."
-[in English] Red?
-Yeah, or "downward."
[speaks Navajo]
[Harold, in English]
Means going up, down into the canyon.
-[Umi, in English] Uh-huh.
-[Harold] So this mesa…
Where that mesa is at,
it goes back into the ground.
[Chaka] Uh-huh.
[Harold] Weaves back.
So it comes up from here, like…
-Like this. And it goes back down.
-[Umi] Uh-huh.
So the definition to it is…
the description is… [speaks Navajo]
[Chaka speaks Navajo]
[Harold, in English] Yeah, it means
"goes back into the ground."
[Chaka, in English] Into the ground.
[Harold] Um, we're here again.
This is called the "Red Land"
or in Navajo we call it… [speaks Navajo]
-[in English] The "Red Land". Yes.
-[speak Navajo]
-No vegetation too much. Everything red.
-[Chaka, Umi, Shizu, in English] Mm-hmm.
The one that we have behind.
What does it look like to you guys?
[Chaka, in English]
That's… that's a family.
-[Harold] A family?
-[Chaka laughs]
-Dad and Mom and children. It's kids.
-Oh.
-[in Japanese] Looks like a "W" to me.
-[Chaka] It's a W.
[Harold, in English] Yeah, they're called
the… In Navajo we call it… [speaks Navajo]
[all speak Navajo]
[Harold, in English]
"Many rocks standing upward." Okay?
But in English translation, we call…
It's called the "Three Sisters".
-[in English] Three Sisters. Uh-huh.
-Like the three Catholic nuns.
-[Harold] Mm-hmm.
-Sisters.
[Harold] But it also looks like a…
a W and a V.
"Welcome visitor to wonderful valley.
Enjoy the wonderful views."
-Wonderful.
-Wonderful. W.
[laughs] Got ya.
-Uh-huh.
-[Shizu] Thank you. [laughs]
Okay, and then we have this
right over here.
[Umi] Mm-hmm.
[Harold] This is called
the John Ford's Point.
-[Umi] Point.
-In Navajo we call it… [speaks Navajo]
[all speak Navajo]
-[in English] The "Pointed Rock." Okay?
-[Umi, in English] Mm-hmm.
But then 1920,
Harry Goulding came out here
and introduced a movie director
by the name of, uh, John Ford,
and started the movies
out here in the '30s and so on.
The Searchers, She Wore a Yellow Ribbon
and Mackenna's Gold.
The list goes on. And so many movies
has been made here and all that.
So, he filmed it from there
and he loved that area,
and that's why it's called
the John Ford's Point.
Mm-hmm.
[in Japanese] During the trip,
we've seen a lot of jewelry
made with precious gemstones
mined from this region.
Could you tell us what significance
these precious stones have
in your culture?
[Harold, in English] Yes.
Um, to the Navajo people and all that,
Diné people,
rock is very close to us and so on.
So when we purchase something,
like jewelries and all that,
turquoise, silvers, or anything like that,
we don't put it in a safe place
or storage.
The reason by it is because we are
in need of it. Then it helps us heal.
And turquoise is very special to us
and all that.
And then it makes us more outgoing,
more energetic and so on.
As well with sterling silver as well.
We're more grounded that way and so on.
And that's one of the reasons
and the philosophy of the Navajo people…
If we have jewelries,
they also need to be breathing.
They also need to socialize
with other jewelries as well.
And so we wear it all the time.
-[in English] Uh-huh. It's interesting.
-[Umi] Yeah, interesting.
Our body choose for a rock or any element,
minerals that we need.
Just like the one that
you're wearing right now.
Your body needs that so you…
attracts to that.
And then you're wearing it right now.
Because everybody
in the Navajo way of life,
-we need to be balanced.
-[Shizu] Mmm.
"Beauty Way" we call it.
Beauty before me, beauty behind me,
beauty above me,
beauty beside me, beauty around me.
And so the way we heal
is by elements or stones
or anything that can heal us internally
and/or physically as well.
-[in Japanese] I had no idea.
-How interesting.
[in English] I see that. [laughs]
[in Japanese] Whoa.
[in English] That's little surprise to us.
That… Those things.
[Harold] Yeah, as you can see, that…
the cloud is above us,
the rain coming down and all that.
We don't get as much rain
as we're supposed to and all that,
so our precipitation about 30 years ago
was about, uh, 30 centimeters.
Now we are lucky to have
about 15 centimeters of rain and all that.
-Wow.
-Throughout the year.
-Yeah.
-Our precipitation is very, very scarce.
-Uh-huh.
-So when we see, um…
um, rain coming down, okay, we enjoy it.
And we uplift and all that.
[Chaka, in English] Oh, I see.
Yeah.
And then right now,
once we get back in the vehicle,
we're gonna go to an area
that we call a restricted area.
-[Shizu] Restricted area.
-Uh, yes.
No public vehicle goes out there
and all that, so…
-Go. Let's go.
-A special place.
-Yeah. Whoa!
-Yes.
-Let's go.
-Let's follow you.
Let's go, boys.
-Can you smell it now?
-[Chaka] Yeah, yeah, good. Rain smell.
-[Umi, in Japanese] Amazing. Mmm.
-[Chaka, in English] That's good smell.
-[Shizu] It's the smell of the rain.
-[Chaka] I can feel ground.
[Umi] Yeah.
[rain pattering]
[in Japanese] How incredible.
[in English] We bring rain to here.
[Harold] Yes.
[rain pattering continues]
-[Harold] Look at the view right here.
-[Umi, Chaka, in English] Mm-hmm.
Everywhere you turn in Monument Valley,
it's always magical.
-Mm-hmm.
-And every place has a hidden area
that is very special
to everybody and all that, so…
This is called the "North Window".
-North Window.
-Yes.
[Chaka] Oh.
This is my homeland.
This is where my ancestral people
came from, Diné people.
My grandparents and their grandparents
and pass on.
My grand… And my parents as well.
So they resided out here
and lived here most of their life,
and lived in this area.
So as a child I explored this area
and I did a lot of wonderful things
out here.
And when I was younger
and all that, so it's…
It means a lot to me.
When I go away, I always want to come back
and look at it again and so on.
[distant jingling]
-[in Japanese] Do you hear the jingling?
-What's that?
[jingling continues]
[Umi, Shime, Chaka, in English] Whoa!
-[Umi, in Japanese] Amazing.
-[Chaka, in English] So cool!
[Umi, in Japanese] Cool!
[drum thumps]
[clears throat] Here it goes.
-[drum thumping]
-[ankle bells jingling]
[Chaka, in Japanese] Wow.
[Harold sings in Navajo]
[singing continues]
[Harold, in English]
Prior to 1868, we protected the land,
we protect the families and so on.
But after June 1st 1868,
we signed a treaty with the government
that we were never going to fight again.
So after that, things changed for us.
But prior to 1960-- 1868, excuse me, 1868,
protecting the land and family…
that's what we use and obtain and all that
so the, the people become warriors.
They have to be brave enough
to go into an enemy camp
and get something from the enemy camp
and bring it back.
And that's how they earned their feathers.
Majority of the people,
they like to do prayers.
Early morning prayers.
Afternoon, evening prayers and so on.
They… They want some kind of
an affirmation in their life and so on.
[drumming, singing continue]
So the moral of the stories back then,
a lot of Native American raided
each other and…
But during the Spanish era and all that,
they came out here
and tried to invade the Native Americans.
And so by force we had
to take them back out there and all that.
But they also introduced
their horses to us
and that's how we're trying to obtain it.
So through lightning and thunder,
we obtain the horses and all that.
Thunder and all that. So,
as rain come down with all that water
coming down, with all the lightning,
with all the thunders and all that,
that was our advantage for us
to take the horses
without being detected at nighttime.
So the lightning come give us a flash.
The light that we need.
The noise that the horse make,
the thunders and everything blends it out.
And then the rain when we ride them out,
the rain just washes everything out.
And that's how
we obtained the horses and all that.
So this song is pertaining to that
and all that so…
[drumming, singing ends]
[in English] Why did you decide the…
do the dancing?
Well, I wanna get connected
to my Native… Native fate.
So I just think that has you become
more connected with your nature
or your Native nature is…
just grass dance or powwow dancing.
It connects with people.
Helps you connect with earth
as you meet all kinds of people
from other tribes and many other things.
So I wanted to be connected. Just have
my regular trace, follow my culture.
[Umi, in English] Hmm.
-[Chaka, in English] I respect you.
-[Umi] Yeah.
[Chaka] That's great.
-[Shizu] Very nice.
-[Chaka] That was amazing.
-Yeah.
-Yes.
Thank you so much.
-[Chaka] You wanna shake hand?
-Yeah.
-[Chaka] Thank you.
-[Shizu] Thank you.
-[Umi] Thank you so much.
-You're welcome.
-[Shizu] You're a great dancer.
-[Chaka] Yeah.
-[Shizu] Thank you.
-[Harold] You're welcome.
[in Japanese] These traditional…
[clears throat]
…dance and song are how the Navajo tribe
have passed down their culture
from one generation to the next.
Over time, it painted their history.
Yeah.
I got to experience
their culture firsthand.
-They express this breathtaking nature…
-Yeah.
…through music and dance. The music too.
It's vastly different from the pop music
we create, or what's trending.
-No.
-Yeah, there's nothing quite like it.
It's their rendition of the music
bestowed upon them by Mother Earth.
-Such a refreshing spin on music.
-Mm-hmm.
I agree.
-It was a breath of fresh air.
-Right.
What an incredible,
once-in-a-lifetime experience.
I agree.
Right?
That dance blurs the boundary
between tradition and entertainment.
But dance and music are universal,
you know?
I agree. Yes.
It left me with a sense of wonder.
We live in a vast world.
It's full of wonders
we've yet to discover.
I agree.
[♪ serene music plays]
[♪ music continues]
[♪ music stops]
[♪ Harold sings in Navajo]
[♪ singing continues]
[♪ singing stops]
[Harold exclaims]
[exclaims]
[distant exclaiming]
Hello.
[in English] Hello. Nice to meet you.
I'm Chaka. Nice to meet you.
I'm Shizu.
Nice to meet you. I'm Umi.
I'm Rahelio.
Rahelio. Nice to meet you.
-I'm gonna take you someplace special, so…
-Oh, really?
Vibration through your body.
Take you into a meditation experience.
-Meditation.
-Meditation, yeah.
[Rahelio]
This is the Thunder Mountain right here.
-[Umi] Mm-hmm.
-[Chaka] Whoa.
[Rahelio] The Sky Father speaks
with thunder, so this is like this…
Very powerful place.
Lightning hits here all the time.
It's a very powerful mountain.
And we're gonna go down, do
a little blessing ceremony and a little…
and a meditation for you.
And kind of guide you.
[in Japanese] Look, a mountain path.
[Umi] Amazing.
[Rahelio vocalizes]
It's like walking on the Mother Earth.
Mother Earth is a living consciousness.
Human beings have forgotten
that the Mother Earth is alive.
As we become more conscious with her,
uh, we'll have much more prosperity,
more success.
Right now the world… people are exploiting
the earth and treating it as a commodity.
But the earth is living,
and as we walk the wheel…
[all vocalizing]
[Rahelio] I built this wheel 21 years ago.
When we walk the wheel,
we're walking a prayer.
[Chaka, in English] Mm-hmm.
It's like we're walking prayerfulness
to bless our families,
our communities, our nations.
To bless all sentient beings.
[all vocalizing]
Each step is a prayer.
And where you stop
will be a teaching for you,
a blessing for you where you stop.
On the wheel.
This always seems
to be my place to stop right here,
so stop wherever you feel right.
The wheel is like the galaxy.
Great wheel of stars.
He stands in the east,
a place of new beginning.
"Who am I? Where am I going? What…"
A coming forth
with a new part of your life. Growth.
When is your birthday?
-April.
-[Rahelio] A Taurus?
-Fifteen.
-[Rahelio] Aries?
-Yeah.
-[Rahelio] Aries.
Aries, in Native American zodiac,
is Red Hawk.
Red Hawk people. Red Hawk.
Quick to fly and, "See if I like this.
I'm in. I don't like it. I'm outta here."
It's about finding personal freedom
and self-discovery
by just going forth
and trusting your instincts
for what feels right for you.
So a new beginning.
A new cycle of self-discovery.
When's your birthday?
August 10th.
[Rahelio] This is the place of summer.
The place of growth, support, security.
A community and family connection.
So here is all about family ties
and feeling supported
and secure in who you are.
When's his birthday?
September 22nd.
[Rahelio] A Libra.
This right here is Libra.
This is the midsummer.
It's about creative purpose, creativity,
"Find in my heart what I need to express."
And as you move here, this is more about
refining… refining your life expression
and getting things… You're, like,
working out any kind of creative block.
You just put your energy into focus.
So, it's taking creativity and
channeling it to, like, your perfections.
Your… "This is what I… my routine.
This is how I wanna…
what I'm trying to create like that."
[Rahelio, Umi vocalizing]
[vocalizing continues]
[vocalizing stops]
[drum thumps]
[Rahelio] It's the heartbeat of creation.
[drumming continues]
Totally relaxing.
[Rahelio sings in Navajo]
[drumming, singing continue]
[drumming stops]
-[Rahelio sings in Navajo]
-[bell chimes]
[singing, chiming continue]
-[rattle shakes]
-[♪ flute music plays]
[♪ rattling, music continue]
[♪ rattling, music stop]
Take your time…
-[Rahelio chants in Navajo]
-[drum thumps]
…and come back from the meditation
whenever you want.
[chanting, drumming continue]
[chanting, drumming stop]
[Rahelio speaks Navajo]
[in English] Thank you, thank you.
Be spared. Arigatou.
[♪ serene music plays]
[♪ music continues]
[in Japanese] I feel the "nothingness."
[Rahelio, in English]
The universe came out of nothingness.
It was nothingness, the void,
and then light came forth.
So, out of the nothingness,
creativity comes forth.
[in Japanese] It's, like,
my senses are resting from everything,
and I'm in a space of my own.
It felt serene.
[in English] In the mountains, in nature,
there's natural energy rhythm.
Birds singing, crickets making noise.
Nature has rhythms, like brain waves.
So, to be by the mountain,
by the land, in nature,
it syncs us back to the natural self.
That's where our creativity comes from.
[in Japanese] The vision I had for myself
has become crystal clear again.
I feel
my connection to Mother Earth.
[Rahelio, in English]
You just, uh, trust in your intuition
'cause new opportunities
are coming for you.
So, the more you connect
with your nature within you,
the more your guide will come forth.
[in Japanese] Yes.
-Thank you.
-[Rahelio, in Japanese] Thank you.
[all singing in Navajo]
[singing continues]
[singing stops]
-[Rahelio, in English] Ooh.
-[Umi, Shizu, Chaka] Ooh.
[rattles shake]
We're singing to the Sky Father
to bless the circle of life.
-Up there.
-Okay.
The world has been broken by war
and conflict and negative energy.
So that song is
to renew the circle of life.
[Shizu] Hmm.
[♪ serene music plays]
[♪ music continues]
[Noel, in Japanese]
I wonder if everyone has had some clarity.
I can't wait to meet up with them
and hear all their stories.
[♪ music stops]
Translated by Megumi Hunter